Guide to the John Greenleaf Whittier Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Greenleaf Whittier Collection
1831-1942
1837-1892
YCAL MSS 986
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.92
(4 boxes) + 1 broadside
Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Abel Cary Thomas Gift, 1832-1934. II. Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, 1844-1888. III. Material from Other Sources, 1831-1942.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
John Greenleaf Whittier (1807-1892)
John Greenleaf Whittier, American poet and abolitionist. Known as America's "Quaker poet," Whittier was a prolific writer who produced more than forty volumes of poetry and prose during his lifetime. Summary information is available in the standard print and online biographical resources.
Scope and Contents
The John Greenleaf Whittier collection contains correspondence, writings, and other papers by or relating to the nineteenth-century American poet and abolitionist John Greenleaf Whittier. Correspondence consists entirely of autograph letters, signed or initialed. Writings include autograph manuscript drafts or copies of poems and proofs, many also signed or initialed. Other papers include artistic and photographic portraits of Whittier.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired primarily through gift from Abel Cary Thomas and Owen Franklin Aldis. For more information, consult the appropriate curator.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 19th century; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 19th century; Poets -- United States -- 19th century; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892
- I. Abel Cary Thomas Gift, 1832-1934; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged by volume number.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Abel Cary Thomas Gift, consists of letters and drafts of poems by Whittier housed in two volumes. Volume 1 contains autograph letters, signed or initialed, arranged alphabetically by name of recipient. Volume 2 is subdivided for autograph manuscript writings, also signed or initialed, and autograph letters, signed.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Abel Cary Thomas, date unknown.
  - VOLUME 1
    - Alexander, Francis, 1869 August 4 (Box 1)
      Includes draft, autograph, of poem "To Garibaldi"
    - Alexander, Lucia Gray Sweet, 1867-1882 (Box 1)
      General
      See: Swett, Lucia Gray
    - Bowditch, Henry I. (Henry Ingersoll), 1846-1871 (Box 1)
    - Bowen, Clarence Winthrop, 1886, 1888 (Box 1)
    - [Burr, J. V.?], 1883 December 5 (Box 1)
    - [Cate?], Mrs., 1887 April 24 (Box 1)
    - Chapman, Mrs., 1875 March 10 (Box 1)
    - Child, Lydia Maria, 1874 June 29 (Box 1)
    - Claflin, Mary B. (Mary Bucklin), 1879, 1883 (Box 1)
    - Claflin, William, [1874 April 4?] (Box 1)
    - Fields, Annie, n.y. January 29 (Box 1)
    - Fields, James Thomas, 1853-1866 (Box 1)
    - Fussell, B., 1839 November 25 (Box 1)
    - Gilder, [Jeannette L. (Jeannette Leonard)?], 1881 June 27 (Box 1)
    - Hayne, Paul Hamilton, 1873-1879, undated (Box 1)
    - Hooper, Joseph, 1888 December 11 (Box 1)
    - Hooper, Lucy, 1837 August 17 (Box 1)
    - [Howell], Elizabeth [Lloyd], 1870 October 21
      See: Lloyod, Elizabeth
    - Kauffman, S. H., [1867] May 18 (Box 1)
    - Lloyd, Elizabeth, 1870 October 21 (Box 1)
    - Swett, Lucia Gray, 1867-1882 (Box 1)
  - VOLUME 2
    - Writings
      - "Bayard Taylor," third stanza, autograph manuscript, signed, 1880 April 6 (Box 2)
      - "The Brown Dwarf of Rugen," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - "Brown of Ossawatemie," autograph manuscript, initialed, undated (Box 2)
      - ["I pray the prayer of Plato old..."], autograph manuscript, signed, [1852] (Box 2)
      - "My Triumph," stanzas VIII-IX, autograph manuscript, corrected and signed, 1879 (Box 2)
      - ["Not vainly in the persian clime..."], autograph manuscript, signed, 1878 May 15 (Box 2)
      - ["Our lines are albums. As we turn..."], autograph manuscript, signed, 1862 February 26 (Box 2)
      - "Seed-time and Harvest," third stanza, autograph manuscript, signed, 1849 October 22 (Box 2)
      - ["To the brave, the elements..."], autograph manuscript, signed, 1864 January 14 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - ----, Horace, 1871 (Box 2)
      - ----, Lizzie, undated (Box 2)
      - Unidentified, 1859-1890, undated (Box 2)
      - Parsons, Sarah Maria, 1881 February 16 (Box 2)
      - Pfeiffer, Emily, 188[5?] May 10 (Box 2)
      - Piatt, John James, 1875 December 7 (Box 2)
      - Robinson, William S., 1848 August 14 (Box 2)
      - Rockwell, J. A., 1832 July 28 (Box 2)
      - St. Charles Leader, 1877 September 12 (Box 2)
      - Scribner's Monthly, 1879 June 15 (Box 2)
      - Spofford, Harriet Elizabeth Prescott, undated (Box 2)
      - Sturtevant, Mrs., 1886 May 31 (Box 2)
      - Underwood, Francis Henry, 1882 June 2 (Box 2)
      - Walker, Francis Amasa, 1885 Februrary 19 (Box 2)
      - Weeks, ----, 1884 June 1 (Box 2)
      - Whipple, Edwin Percy, 1883 May 9 (Box 2)
      - Unidentified, 1868-1883, undated (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous material, 1866-1892, undated (Box 2)
        Includes photographs and printed ephemera
    - Other Papers
      - Miscellaneous material, 1866-1892, undated (Box 2)
      - Material removed from volume, 1922-1934, undated (Box 2)
- II. Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, 1844-1888; 0.21
  Gift of Owen Franklin Aldis, 1911.
  Series II, Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, consists of letters and writings by Whittier. The series is subdivided for autograph letters, signed, and writings, which include drafts of poems, autograph manuscript, signed or initialed, and a page proof for the Introduction to Edwin Percy Whipple's American Literature (Boston: Ticknor and Company, 1887), with annotations in Whittier's hand.
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Writings.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Aldis, A. O., 1860, 1862 (Box 3)
    - Ames, "Miss", 1887 December 21 (Box 3)
    - [Carter, Mary E.], undated (Box 3)
    - Clarke, James F., 1863 June 30 (Box 3)
    - Fields, [James Thomas?], 1856 January 24 (Box 3)
    - Johnson, Mr., 1888 September 16 (Box 3)
    - Larcom, Lucy, 1867, 1883 (Box 3)
    - Linton, W. J. (William James), 1877 February 3 (Box 3)
    - Macy, Fanny M., 1878 March 24 (Box 3)
    - Marsh, O. C. (Othniel Charles), 1856 July 8 (Box 3)
    - Tracy, Mr. and Mrs., 1857 March 10 (Box 3)
    - Tracy, Thomas, 1845 November 8 (Box 3)
    - Underwood, Francis Henry, 1882 July 8 (Box 3)
    - Waterston, R. C. (Robert Cassie), 1844 October 10 (Box 3)
    - Unidentified, 1857-1886 (Box 3)
  - WRITINGS
    - ["Faith shares the future's promise: love's..."], autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 3)
    - "Introduction" to Edwin Percy Whipple's American Literature (Boston: Ticknor and Company, 1887), page proofs, with corrections and annotations in Whittier's hand, circa 1886 (Box 3)
    - ["Keep who will the city's alleys..."], autograph manuscript, initialed, 1855 November 18 (Box 3)
    - "My Playmate," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, circa 1859 (Box 3)
      Poem on verso of ALS, dated 24 December 1859, from William [Cullen] Bryant
    - ["Shew thy vacant tomb..."], autograph manuscript, signed, 1871 February 5 (Box 3)
- III. Material from Other Sources, 1831-1942; 0.21
  Acquired from various sources. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
  Organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers.
  Series III, Material from Other Sources, includes correspondence from Whittier, writings by Whittier, and other papers. There are additional autograph letters, signed, and autograph manuscript drafts and proofs of writings, some also signed, as well as artisitic and photographic portraits of Whittier.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Cartland, Gertrude, 1876 May 10 (Box 3)
      Includes third party letters from Martha Hale Shackford to John A. Pollard, dated 1949, and from John A. Pollard to Donald Gallup, dated 1963
    - Child, Calvin Goddard, 1861 October 18 (Box 3)
    - Deming, Clarence, 1880 December 30 (Box 3)
    - Dorrance, Mr., 1866 January 10 (Box 3)
    - Fowler, William Worthington, 1870 May 28 (Box 3)
    - International Review, 1877 (Box 3)
    - Ives, Frederick O., 1879 January 14 (Box 3)
    - Lane, George Martin, 1858 April 26 (Box 3)
    - Law, Jonathan; Law, Mrs., 1836, undated (Box 3)
    - Lowell, James Russell, 1857-1858 (Box 3)
    - Neally, Mary E., 1882 August 16 (Box 3)
    - Parsons, S. Maria, 1882 February 25 (Box 3)
    - Russ, [Cornelia], undated (Box 3)
      Contains typescript copy of letter and clippings dating from 1944
    - Stedman, Frederick Stuart, 1874 October 24 (Box 3)
    - Tilton, Theodore, 1866 October 14 (Box 3)
    - Todd, Dr., 183[1?] September 20 (Box 3)
    - Tufts, H., 1876 June 4 (Box 3)
    - Unidentified, 1858-1891, undated (Box 3)
  - WRITINGS
    - ["Anothing hand is beckoning us..."], autograph manuscript (photostat), circa 1941 (Box 3)
    - ["As on wave-washed strand or..."], autograph manuscript, signed, 1890 January 20 (Box 3)
    - "Clarkson," autograph manuscript, corrected and signed, 1864 October 18 (Box 3)
    - "The Cry of a Lost Soul," Portugese translation, "O choro d'uma alma perdida" by Dom Pedro, autograph manuscript (photostat), undated (Box 3)
      Includes correspondence about the poem and translation
    - "Moloch in State Street," autograph manuscript, corrected and initialed, undated
    - "One of the Signers," autograph manuscript (incomplete), undated (Box 3)
    - "An Outdoor Reception," autograph manuscript, corrected and signed, and galley proof, corrected, undated (Box 3)
    - ["So do thy work. It shall succeed..."], autograph manuscript, signed, 1867 December 20 (Box 3)
    - "Theirs," autograph manuscript, corrected, circa 1878 January (Box 3)
    - "The Vow of Washington," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Autograph signatures, undated (Box 3)
    - Check, completed to L. H. Caldwell and signed, 1888 August 24 (Box 3)
    - Clipping, 1942 November 11
    - Portrait engraving of Whittier, undated (Box 3)
    - Portrait lithograph of Whittier by Joseph E. Baker, 1877 (Box 4 (Broadside))
    - Portrait photograph of Whittier, undated (Box 3)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Material removed from volume (In Series I), 1922, 1934 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - "Introduction" to Edwin Percy Whipple's American Literature (Boston: Ticknor and Company, 1887), page proofs, with corrections and annotations in Whittier's hand (In Series II), circa 1886 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - "Moloch in State Street," autograph manuscript, corrected and initialed (In Series III), undated (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - "An Outdoor Reception," galley proof, corrected (In Series III), undated (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Clipping (In Series III), 1942 November 11 (Box 5 (Oversize))